Guide to the World War I Pamphlet Collection 1901-1944 (bulk 1914-1919)
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
World War I Pamphlet Collection
1901-1944 (bulk 1914-1919)
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Pam 01
20.75 linear feet
A collection of approximately 2,000 pamphlets, magazines, booklet and book-length literature, maps, posters, and cartoons published during the"Great War" or immediately thereafter.
Historical Note
A collection of pamphlets, magazines, booklets and book-length literature, maps, posters, and cartoons dealing with political issues of the First World War.
This is a collection of materials directly related to and largely produced during World War I, the "Great War." Included are official government publications and items from private organizations such as patriotic societies, pacifist and religious leagues, humanitarian associations and special interest groups. They represent a wide range of opinion from German, Danish, English, French, Swedish, Italian and Spanish sources. According to provenance documents, these pamphlets were used by peace negotiators for the Treaty of Versailles.
This collection has been organized alphabetically by country of origin or subject and then chronologically when feasible. Although the grouping has been categorized and sorted at the folder level, item-level descriptive information has been drawn from records available in WorldCat.
Note that entries exist for Europe. This part of the collection contains information relating to the Versailles settlement of 1919. Fascist propaganda during the late interwar period is grouped under its source. Atrocity literature has been grouped under the source country of the allegation rather than the subject country; e.g., atrocities alleged by Belgium against Germany would be found under Belgium.
Other propaganda may be found under its source if the subject is primarily of national concern to the originating nation, such as a national issue like the wartime Spanish elections in which Spain's neutrality was a political issue. Because of the peculiar role played by the United States before and after its entry into the war, much of its literature is categorized as Pre-war, Wartime, and Post-war.
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
These materials were held by the Library of Congress prior to their transfer to The University of Montana in 1975.
The acquistion of the bulk of this collection of duplicate pamphlets and other publications originally acquired by the Library of Congress was facilitated by Montana Senator Lee Metcalf and University of Montana Professor Paul G. Lauren.
The oversized materials in OS 46 were not part of the original acquisition from the Library of Congress, and their custodial history is unknown.
The Martian newspaper was donated by Asa L. Duncan.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1914-1918--Propaganda
International Relations
- Albania - Foreign Politics: Independence Concerns (in English), 1919; Pandele, Anastas. An Appeal to the Government and People of America by the Albanian Federation of America, Vatra. 1919.; Erickson, C. Telford. Moral Leadership in World Reconstruction. Congress Hall Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1919.; Erickson, C. Telford. Cutting the Gorgon Knot. Congress Hall Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1919. (Box-folder 1/1)
- Albania - Foreign Politics: Territory Questions (in French), 1919; Mexi, Hristo. Mémorandum à l'usage de monsieur le président et de messieurs les membres de la Conférence de la paix: ainsi qu'á celui des commissions accessoires. Bucarest: Institut d'arts graphyques "Speranta", 1919. (Relativement aux droits de revendication des Albanais originaires des territoires restés en dehors des frontières détérminées par les Conférences de Londres et de Florence en 1913 à l'occasion de la création de l'état Albanais.) (Box-folder 1/2)
- Armenia - Atrocities Alleged: Against Turkey (in English), 1904; Eyewitness Report upon the Armenian Situation and Massacres of 1904. Barton, James L. 1904. (extremely fragile; The following extracts are taken from communications received by James L. Barton, Secretary of the American Board at Boston, MA., from missionaries of that Board stationed in different parts of Turkey. If public use is made of these articles it is essential, in most cases, that the writer be not revealed, for fear such a disclosure might bring trouble if no peril upon him.) (Box-folder 1/3)
- Armenia - Atrocities Alleged: Against Turkey (in English), 1918 and undated; Armenian Bureau. Turkish Enormities: Appeal by the Armenian National Delegation. London: Spottiswoode, Ballantyne & Co. Ltd.,; Varandian, Mikael. The Tragedy of the Caucasus: Memorandum Presented to the 18th Annual Conference of the British Labour Party. London: 1918.; Armenian National Defence Committee of America. Wholesale Massacred of Men, Women and Children Ordered, Says Primate-Many Plunged Into Prisoners-The Euphrates Roads Strewn with Corpses. U.S.A.: n.d. (2 copies) (Box-folder 1/4)
- Armenia - Atrocities Alleged: Against Turkey (in French), 1916 and undated; Comité suisse de secours aux Arméniens. Quelques documents sur le sort des Arméniens en 1915-16. n. d.; Andreasian, Dikran. Comment un drapeau sauva quatre mille Arméniens. Paris: Fischbacher, 1916. (Box-folder 1/5)
- Armenia - Atrocities Alleged: Against Turkey (in French), 1920; Témoignages inédits sur les atrocités turques commises en Arménie, suivis d'un récit de l'épopée arménienne de Chabin-Karahissar recueillis par la Société des dames Arméniennes (Azkanever de Constantinople). Paris: Dubreuil, Frerebeau et Ciecle, 1920. (2 copies); Bulletin arménien. 1920. (extremely fragile; loose newspaper article) (Box-folder 1/6)
- Armenia - Atrocities Alleged: Personal Narrative (in English), 1917-1918; Mugerditchian, Esther. From Turkish Toils: The Narrative of an Armenian Family's Escape. New York: G.H. Doran Co, 1917. (Translated from the Armenian with portraits); Ghuṣayn, Fa'iz. Martyred Armenia. New York: George H. Doran Co, 1918. (Translated from the Original Arabic) (Box-folder 1/7)
- Armenia - Atrocities Alleged: Personal Narrative (in English), 1918; Mardiganian, Aurora, and H. L. Gates. Ravished Armenia, The Story of Aurora Mardiganian, the Christian Girl Who Lived Through the Great Massacres. New York: Kingfield, 1918. (Four Illustrations from Photographs and a Map of the District) (Box-folder 1/8)
- Armenia - Atrocities Alleged: Personal Narrative (in English), 1919; Lamson, Armenouhie Tashjian. The Story of Crucified Armenia: Little Nation Living Symbol of Suffering for Hundreds of Years, Says Native. Seattle: Seattle Daily Times, 1919. (Box OS 43)
- Armenia - Atrocities Alleged: Personal Narrative (in Italian), 1917; Santamaria, Pietro. I Massacri Armeni: Dichiarazioni di Testimoni Oculari. London: Eyre and Spottiswoode, Ltd., 1917 (Box-folder 1/9)
- Armenia - Foreign Politics: Independence Concerns (in English), 1918-1919 and undated; Velimirovic ́ D.D., Rev. Fr. Nikolaj. The Children of the Illuminator. London: Spottiswoode, Ballantyne & Co. Ltd.,1919. (with photographs and illustrations); V. C. The Case of Armenia. New York: The Armenian National Union of America, 1918.; The American Committee for Armenian Independence. Petition for the Independence of United Armenia. (blank form) (Box-folder 1/10)
- Armenia - Foreign Politics: Independence Concerns (in French), 1919 and undated; Dervichyan, Y. A. Réflexions sur les origines des races en Turquie et leurs incompatibilités. Lausanne: Imprimeries réunies, 1919.; Comité de l'Indépendance Kurde. Kurdistan ou Arménie, tyrans ou martyrs. Le Caire: Imprimerie Paul Barbey, 1919. (fragile; 2 copies); Communications avec l'Armenie. n. d. (typed letter/report) (Box-folder 1/11)
- Armenia - Foreign Politics: Independence Concerns (in German), 1916; Niepage, Martin. Material zur Beurteilung des Schicksals der Armenier im Jahre 1915/16. Amsterdam: Schweizerisches Hilfswerk 1915 für Armenien, 1916. (2 copies) (Box-folder 1/12)
- Australia - Celebrations (in English), 1918-1919; Pritchard, Les H. Lest We Forget, Anzac Day Souvenir. Perth, W.A.: Returned Soldiers' & Sailors' Association of W.A., 1918.; The University of Sydney garden party to welcome returned university soldiers, Wednesday, October 29th, 1919. Sydney: W.E. Smith, 1919. (Box-folder 1/13)
- Australia - Economics and Finance (in English), 1918 and undated; Von Hagen, C. Australia's Share in the War and Who Pays for It? [Sydney]: Executive of Australian Labor Party, State of New South Wales, 1918.; After-War Settlement Series. "The Empire Outlook". St. Albans: The Salvation Army Printing Works. (2 copies); After-War Settlement Series. "The Laughing Jackass and Some Pals". St. Albans: the Salvation Army Printing Works. (2 copies) (Box-folder 1/14)
- Australia - Foreign Politics: Irish Question (in English), circa 1900s; O'Briain, Cearball. Dr. Mannix in Australia: The Brief Story of Seven Strenuous Years Under the Southern Cross. Dublin: Mahon's Printing Works, 1900s. (Box-folder 1/15)
- Austria-Hungary - Domestic Politics: Blockades / Food (in English and German), 1918-1919; Buxton, D. The death of a people: the story of the Austrian famine. London: Fight the Famine Council, 1919.; Nuse, Karl. Die Sicherung der Ernahrung der Mittelmachte durch gemeinsame Ausbringung: Die Allgemeine Nahrpflicht. Deutschen Vereins fur Volksernahrung, 1918. (Box-folder 1/16)
- Austria-Hungary - Domestic Politics: Tourism (in German), 1928; Tschohl, Michael. Schruns im Montafon (Vorarlberg). Schruns: Verkehrsverein, 1928. (Box-folder 1/17)
- Austria-Hungary - Foreign Politics (in English), 1915; Apponyi, Count Albert. Austria-Hungary and the War. New York: Austro-Hungarian Consulate-General, 1915. (2 copies); Austrian and Hungarian Notabilities on the War: Supplement to "The Continental Times". Berlin: Continental Times, 1915.; Austro-Hungarian Monarchy. Collection of Evidence Concerning the Violations of International Law By the Countries at War with Austria-Hungary. Concluded on Jnuary 31, 1915. 1915.; Austria. Italy on the Path of War. Imperial and Royal Austro-Hungarian Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 1915. (Box-folder 1/18)
- Austria-Hungary - Foreign Politics (in German), 1916-1917; Kriegsministeriums Abt. Bestimmungen Fur Die Beistellung Kriegsgefangener Arbeiter in Osterreich. Wien.: Herausgegeben vom k. u. k. Kriegsministerium, 1916.; Stolper, Gustav. Wir und Deutschland. Wien: F. Deuticke, 1917. (Box-folder 1/19)
- Austria-Hungary - Foreign Politics (in German), 1929; Uebersberger, Dr. Hans. Die osterreichische Aktenpublikation zur Vorgeschichte des Weltkrieges. Wien: 1929. (Box-folder 1/20)
- Austria-Hungary - Foreign Politics: Territory Questions (in English), 1926 and undated; Marczali, Dr. Henry and Imre Radvanyi. The Tragedy of Hungary: The greatest injustice of the Worlds History. 1926.; A Few Facts about Hungary. (Do you care about Truth and Justice?) n.d. (2 copies) (Box-folder 1/21)
- Austria-Hungary - Foreign Politics: Territory Questions (in German), 1919; Pethoe, Sándor. Strasbourg-Metz, Presbourg-Kassa; Par Alexandre Petho. Ligue Pour l'Integrite Territoriale de la Hongrie, 1919.; Schwoner, Alfred. Sollen wir uns an Deutschland anschliessen? Wien: L. Heidrich, 1919. (Box-folder 1/22)
- Austria-Hungary - Military (in German), 1916 and undated; J, E. v. Ein Jahr italienischer Krieg. Wien: Seidel, 1916.; Puecher, Edmund. Welche Rechtsanspruche auf Versorgungsbezuge haben die Kriegsinvaliden u. die Kriegshinterbliebenen in Osterreich? Die kustenlandische Landeskommission fur heimkehrende Krieger in Triest, 1916.; Das Schlagwort vom Militarismus. Wien: Dr. Pimmer, n.d. (Box-folder 1/23)
- Austria-Hungary - Military: Battles & Campaigns (in German), 1917-1918; Italiens Militarischer Zusammenbruch Im Okt.-Nov. 1917. Berlin, 1917.; Die 12. Isonzo Schlacht. Berlin: Karl Curtis Verlag, 1918. (The Battle of Isonzo, maps and pictures in this pamphlet) (Box-folder 2/1)
- Austria-Hungary - Patriotic Propaganda (in German), 1915; Witwen- und Waisen-Hilfsfond (Austria). Almanach des Kriegsjahres: der patriotischen Frauen Osterreichs. Wien: Julius Brull, 1915. (Translation: "Almanac of the year of the war: the patriotic women of Austria". Poems, stories and other propaganda written by Austrian women.) (Box-folder 2/2)
- Austria-Hungary - War Relief Efforts: American Aid (in English), 1915; Firquet von Cesenatico. Open Letter to Dr. Arthur Howell Gerhard in Philadelphia. Berlin: C. White, 1915. (2 copies) (extremely fragile) (Box-folder 2/3)
- Austria-Hungary - War Relief Efforts: American Aid (in German), 1920; Birquet, Dr. Clemens. Die Amerikanische Hilfsaktion in Osterreich. 1920. (extremely fragile) (Box-folder 2/4)
- Austria-Hungary - War Relief Efforts: War Refugees (in German), 1917; Zentralstelle der Fursorge fur Kriegsflüchtlinge. Wien: 1917. (pamphlet title translates "Central Office of caring for war refugees from Galicia & Bukowina; pamphlet about Jewish refugees) (Box-folder 2/5)
- Belgium - Atrocities / Deportations (in English), 1914-1915 and undated; Roedel, Emil. Belgium Under German Administration. Los Angeles: [n.p.], 1915.; Seaman, Louis Livingston. The Crucifixion of Belgium: An Address on Germany's Deportation of the Innocent People of Belgium and Northern France. 1914.; Cooreman, Gerard. The Martyrdom of Belgium Official Report of Massacres of Peaceable Citizens, Women and Children, by the German Army: Testimony of Eyewitnesses. Baltimore: The W. Stewart Brown Company, Inc., 1915. (2 copies); An eye-witness at Louvain. London: Eyre & Spottiswoode, LTD., 1914.; Essen, Léon van der. A Statement About the Destruction of Louvain and Neighborhood. Chicago: Priv. Print, 1915.; Translation of a letter received from a young Belgian boy of about 16 years of age. Written in Antwerp, September 23, 1914. Received in England, September 28, 1914.; Germany's Latest Crime: The Enslavement of Belgians. Life Pub. Co., n.d. (Box-folder 2/6)
- Belgium - Atrocities / Deportations (in English), 1916; Civilians of Brussels Victims to German Artillery Fire. London: W. Speaight & Sons, 1916. (2 copies); Malcolm, Ian. Scraps of Paper: German Proclamations in Belgium and France. London: Hodder and Stoughton, 1916. (Box-folder 2/7)
- Belgium - Atrocities / Deportations (in English), 1916; Malcolm, Ian. Scraps of Paper: German Proclamations in Belgium and France. London: Hodder and Stoughton, 1916. (Box OS 43)
- Belgium - Atrocities / Deportations (in English), 1916-1917; The Belgian deportations: facsimiles of clandestine leaflets in French and Flemish by means of which the Belgian population encourages itself to passive resistance in occupied Belgium (end of November 1916). Belgian curiosities of war, 6. S.l: s.n, 1916.; The Belgian Deportations: Three German Documents Concerning the Recruiting and Forced Labour of Belgian Workmen. Belgian curiosities of war, 11. S.l: s.n, 1917. (2 copies); The Collective Responsibility of Families: As a Means of Action by the German Administration in Occupied Belgium. Belgian curiosities of war, 12. S.l: s.n, 1917. (2 copies); Cry of Distress and Patriotism from a Belgian Deportee. Belgian curiosities of war, 43. S.l: s.n, 1917. (2 copies); What a Town Can Suffer Under German Rule. Dinant. Curiosities of war, 14 (June 1917). S.l: s.n, 1917. (2 copies); A German Diptych: How th Germans treated the Belgian historian H. Pirenne, 18 months before the declaration of war and 18 months after. Belgian curiosities of war, 45. S.l: s.n, 1917.; A Heart-Breaking Document: regarding the deportation and forced labour of Belgians behind the German front in France. Belgian curiosities of war, 18. S.l: s.n, 1917. (Box-folder 2/8)
- Belgium - Atrocities/Deportations (in English), 1917; Toynbee, Arnold Joseph. The German Terror in Belgium: An Historical Record by Arnold J. Toynbee. London: Hodder & Stoughton, 1917. (Box-folder 2/9)
- Belgium - Atrocities / Deportations (in English), 1917; Memorandum of the Belgian Government on the Deportation and Forced Labour of the Belgian Civil Population Ordered by the German Government. London: Furnival Press, 1917.; United States, and Brand Whitlock. The Deportations: Statement by the American Minister to Belgium. London: T.F. Unwin, 1917.; Cammaerts, Emile, and Louis Raemaekers. Through the Iron Bars (Two Years of German Occupation in Belgium). London: John Lane, 1917.; Allen, George Henry, and Henry C. Whitehead. Extracts from Official Reports Issued by Belligerent Governments Offered in Evidence of Alleged Violations of the Laws and Customs of War and of Private Rights: Supplement to The Great War. Philadelphia: G. Barrie, 1917. (eye-witness reports from Belgians) (Box-folder 2/10)
- Belgium - Atrocities / Deportations (in English, French, German and Hebrew), 1919; Jewish War Refugees Committee. Return of Refugees to Belgium. 1919. (in English and Hebrew); Ghent. Commission locale de secours et d'assistance aux réquisitionnés. Opgeeischten van Gent. Réquisitionnés de Gand. Requisitioned civilians of Ghent. Belgie - Belgique - Belgium. Da barbaarsche behandelingen der Duitschers. (Verzamelingen van bewijzen gedurende de bezetting opgemaakt). 1919. (fragile) (Box-folder 2/11)
- Belgium - Atrocities / Deportations (in French, Spanish and Swedish), 1915-1917; Anacharsis. La terreur en Belgique et dans la Prusse orientale: Seconde Partie. Monaco: Imprimeries artistiques réunies, 1915.; Encore une fleur de la culture allemande. 1916. (letter written to a German general by a Belgian woman whose house was burned and husband was killed by German forces); Mercier, Désiré, and Désiré Mercier. Protesta del episcopado belga contra las deportaciones en Bélgica. Londres: Hayman Christy & Lilly, 1917.; Las hazañas de los francotiradores en Bélgica: según los relatos de la misma prensa belga. Barcelona: "La Académica" Serra hermanos y Russell, 1915; Bryce, James, Vt. Senaste akten i det belgiska dramat. Bryce, [James] Vt. 1917. (Box-folder 2/12)
- Belgium - Celebrations (in Dutch, English and French), 1916-1918; Deploige. La Resurrection de Louvain. Paris, 1918.; Hymans, Paul, H. H. Asquith, and Eugène H. G. Standaert. Féte nationale belge. Belgian Independence Day. Belgische onafhankelykheidsdag. Discours prononcés au Royal Albert Hall. Addresses delivered at the Royal Albert Hall. Redevoeringen uitgesproken in den Royal Albert Hall. 1916. (Box-folder 2/13)
- Belgium - Domestic Politics (in Danish, French, Italian and Spanish), 1917 and undated; Opraab fra de belgiske arbejdere: til arbejderne af alle nationer. London: Eyre and Spottiswoode, 1917. (2 copies); La Constitution Belge. Imp. J. Janssens. Bruxelles: J. Lebegue and Cie, n.d.; Agli operai di tutte le nazioni: appello degli operai belghe. London: Hayman, Christy & Lilly, 1917. (Pamphlet about the Belgian Labor Movement); L' œuvre du gouvernement belge pendant la guerre activité des divers départements ministériels by Belgium. Bureau documentaire. Le Havre: O. Randolet, 1917.; Manifiesto de los obreros belgas: á los obreros de todas las naciones. Londres: Eyre and Spottiswoode, 1917. (pamphlet about the Belgian Labor Movement) (Box-folder 2/14)
- Belgium - Foreign Politics (in English), 1914; Belgium. Diplomatic Correspondence Respecting the War Published by the Belgian Government. Miscellaneous, No. 12 (1914). London: Harrison and Sons, 1914. (2 copies) (Box-folder 2/15)
- Belgium - Foreign Politics (in French), 1914 and undated; Pourquoi la guerre: La Belgique et son role dans la guerre actuelle, commenté d'après les documents officiels. La Grande Guerre Européenne / (Verf.: A. L.), [2]. Ixelles: Libr. ancienne et moderne, 1914.; Castelein, E. Le Parlement Anglais et la Belgique: Les requisitions en masse. (2 copies); Documents sur la guerre: Belgique. La question flamande d'apres les Publications allemandes. Paris. (2 copies); Correspondence Belge: Le Havre. (envelope addressed from Le Havre to Holland); Mousieur Georges Desti... Armee Belge. (envelope addressed from the Belgian Army to France); Monsieur Van Langenhove. Chef de Cabinet de Monsieur le Ministre des Affaires Economiques. (envelope addressed from the Belgian Government to Monsieur Van Langenhove) (Box-folder 2/16)
- Belgium - Foreign Politics (in French), 1919-1925; Heyse, Théodore. La Belgique et la polémique sur les origines et les responsabilités de la Guerre. (Heyse: L'Occupation allemande en Belgique, 7). 1925. (2 copies); Vers l'apaisement hollando-belge: commentaires sur les questions relevées vis-à-vis de la Hollande du coté de la Belgique. Bruxelles: Société de Propagande néerlandaise], 1919. (Box-folder 3/1)
- Belgium - Foreign Politics (in German and Swedish), 1914-1918; Det Belgiska Arbetarepartiet. Utlätande om Fredsvillkoren. London: Richard Clay & Sons, 1918.; Banning, Emil, and Emile Banning. Belgier über Belgien: 1. Heft. Die Verteidigung Belgiens vom nationalen und europäischen Standpunkt. Gotha: Perthes, 1917.; Belgium. Belgische aktenstucke, 1905-1914. Berlin: E.S. Mittler und Sohn, 1914. (Box-folder 3/2)
- Belgium - German Occupation (in Dutch), 1917-1918; Goblet d'Alviella, Eugène. Het waar en het valsch pacifisme. Internationale Bibliotheek, no. 6. 's-Gravenhage: "De Hofstad", 1917.; Caine, William. De Geschiedenis van Mijnheer Segotin. London: The Complete Press, 1918. (Box-folder 3/3)
- Belgium - German Occupation (in English), 1914-1915; An Appeal to Truth: A letter addressed by Cardinal Mercier, Archbishop of Malines... London: Hodder & Stoughton, 1915.; Helfferich, Karl. The Condition of Belgium Under the German Occupation. Impressions of a Voyage. Berlin: Liebheit & Thiesen, 1914.; The Innocence of Belgium Established by the Military Documents Published by Germany. S.l: s.n, 1915.; Why Belgium Was Devastated: As Recorded in Proclamations of the German Commanders in Belgium: Extracts from the Official Report of the Belgian Commission of Inquiry. S.l: s.n, 1914.; Belgium. The Facts About Belgium. Washington: Columbian Print. Co., Inc, 1915.; Dernburg, Bernhard. The Case of Belgium In the Light of Official Reports Found in the Secret Archives of the Belgian Government After the Occupation of Brussels. New York: International monthly, 1914. (Box-folder 3/4)
- Belgium - German Occupation (in English), 1918; Cammaerts, Emile, and Henri Davignon. Belgium: I-IV. London: National Home-Reading Union, 1918.; Belgium's Martyrdom. Reprinted from Current History Magazine of the New York Times: 1918. (2 copies); Gauss, Christian Frederick. Some War Curiosities and the Clandestine Press in Belgium. [Historical outlook] War reprint, no. 2. Philadelphia: McKinley Pub. Co, 1918. (Box-folder 3/5)
- Belgium - German Occupation (in English, French and German), 1918; Davignon, Henri. German Posters in Belgium, Their Value As Evidence, New Texts and Documents. Edinburgh: T. Nelson & Sons, 1918. (German posters with English translations); Davignon, Henri. Affiches allemandes en Belgique, leur valeur d'aveu; nouveaux textes et documents précédés d'un avertissement au lecteur. Paris: Pour la vente s'addresser à Hachette & cie, 1918. (German posters with French translations) (Box-folder 3/6)